Guide to the Washington State University Office of the President: Glenn Terrell Inauguration Records and Photographs 1967-1968
Washington State University Libraries Manuscripts, Archives, and Special Collections
Washington State University Office of the President: Glenn Terrell Inauguration Records and Photographs
1967-1968
Washington State University Libraries, Manuscripts, Archives and Special Collections
Archives 162
Washington State University. Office of the President
1 Linear foot of shelf space 2 Boxes
This collection consists of documents used in the planning of W. Glenn Terrell's inauguration in March 1968, letters congratulating Terrell on his new position, and approximately 900 print photographs and 1050 negatives of the inauguration and associated events.
The functions and duties of the Washington State University President are defined in University Faculty Manual, edition of 1987, as:
In addition to being designated as secretary ex officio of the Board of Regents, the President as general agent of the Board is the chief executive officer of Washington State University. The President administers the policies approved by the Board of Regents, serves as advisor to the Board on policies and operations and is the agent through whom representations to the Board are regularly made. Other functions of the chief executive officer include: Leadership in developing policies and organization for teaching, research, and extension programs. Public administration of the University, including representation before the Legislature and other state agencies. Responsibility for the general welfare of students; the development, operation and maintenance of buildings, lands and equipment; financial matters pertaining to development, operation and maintenance of University; and the administration of regulations adopted by the Board of Regents. Responsibility, delegated by the Board of Regents, for all appointments, promotion, salaries, leaves, resignations, and dismissals. Presiding at meetings of the general faculty.
Born 24 May 1920, in Tallahassee, Florida, W. Glenn Terrell earned his bachelor’s degree in political science at Davidson College, his master’s degree in psychology from Florida State University, and his Ph.D. from the University of Iowa. He taught psychology at Florida State and the University of Colorado before becoming dean of the College of Liberal Arts, and then dean of faculties, at the University of Illinois at Chicago Circle.
In 1967, Terrell was selected as the seventh president of Washington State University, taking office on the 1st of July. The years of the Terrell presidency were times of change and turmoil for the nation, including activism on the Pullman campus related to the Vietnam War, racism, and feminism. Terrell is considered to have handled well the difficulties of that era, including the student strike in 1970. Ethnic studies programs, the Commission on the Status of Women, and the Office of Ombudsman, were established by Terrell in response to student and faculty concerns.
Terrell was respected nationally for his leadership, serving on the board of the Western Interstate Commission on Higher Education, or WICHE, and as the elected president of the National Association of State Universities and Land-Grant Colleges.
After his retirement in 1985, and in recognition of his service to WSU, the University established the endowed Glenn Terrell Presidential Scholarships for high-ability students, recognizing both his commitment to students and his role in starting the WSU Foundation. The University also named the area in the heart of the campus the Glenn Terrell Friendship Mall and the new library adjacent to Holland Library as the Terrell Library. Glenn Terrell died at the age of 93 on 30 August 2013.
This collection consists of documents used in the planning of W. Glenn Terrell's inauguration in March 1968, letters congratulating Terrell on his new position, and approximately 900 print photographs and 1050 negatives of the inauguration and associated events.
This collection is arranged into two series: Series 1: Papers, 1967-1968; Series 2: Photographs and Negatives, 1968, arranged chronologically.
This collection is open and available for research use.
Although the materials almost certainly originated from the WSU President's Office, the exact provenance of this collection is unclear. The records were originally kept as a WSU publication (WSU 131). The records were redesignated as University Archives 262, but was not properly arranged or described, before being processed under its current designation.
Two folders were removed from the collection. A set of "Letters from Glenn Terrel" were moved to Washington State University Publications: President's Office (WSU 132) and correspondence dealing with Survey '68 was moved to Folder 146.1 in the Washington State University Office of the President: W. Glenn Terrell Records, 1967-1976 (Archives 205).
Washington State University Office of the President: W. Glenn Terrell Records, 1967-1976 (Archives 205)
Washington State University Office of the President: W. Glenn Terrell Records, 1953-1985 (Archives 207)
Washington State University Office of the President: Assistant to the President Records, 1954-1985 (Archives 216)
Washington State University Office of the President Media, 1937-2006 (Archives 328)
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Terrell, Glenn -- Records and correspondence; Terrell, Glenn
Washington State University. Office of the President -- Records and correspondence; Washington State University -- Presidents -- Records and correspondence
College presidents -- Washington (State) -- Pullman
Colleges and Universities; Washington (State)
- Series 1: Papers, 1967-1968
  - Inauguration Committee, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Guest lists, 1968, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Publications, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Congratulatory letters, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
- Series 2: Photographs and Negatives, 1968
  - Symposium, Todd Auditorium, 1968 March 15 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Luncheon, President's House, 1968 March 16 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Symposium, Todd Auditorium, 1968 March 16 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Inaugural Ball, Stephenson Center, 1968 March 16 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Symposium, Bryan Auditorium, 1968 March 17 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Inaugural Luncheon, Streit-Perham Hall, 1968 March 17 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Inaugural Ceremony, Bohler Gymnasium, 1968 March 17 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Inaugural Reception, Streit-Perham Hall, 1968 March 17 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous and unidentified, 1968 March (Box 2, Folder 15)